Guide to the Edward Claudius Herrick Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Edward Claudius Herrick papers
1797-1862
MS 691
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
8
(15 boxes)
Correspondence, memoranda, notes, and drawings record Herrick's work in astonomy and entomology, particularly his observations on the Aurora Borealis and the Hessian fly. Prominent scientists among his correspondents include Louis Agassiz, James D. Dana, Thaddeus William Harris, Elias Loomis, Lambert Adolphe Jacques Quetelet, William C. Redfield, Samuel H. Scudder, Benjamin Silliman, Benjamin Silliman Jr., and William Tully. His career as librarian of Yale College (1843-1858) is reflected in catalogues, invoices, and memoranda relating to book purchases for the library. Between 1847 and 1862 he also supervised the publication of the triennial catalogues for Yale College and memoranda concerning these are also in the papers. His financial and legal files contain both personal records and account books (1835-1844) for the booksellers' firm of Herrick and Noyes, of which he was a partner. Also included are papers relating to New Haven including minutes of committee meetings, reports and correspondence on the Bicentennial (1838).
Herrick, Edward Claudius, 1811-1862
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Beinecke Rare Book Library in 1973.
Arrangement
Arranged in five series: I. Correspondence. II. Scientific Files. III. Yale University Files. IV. Financial and Legal Files. V. Miscellaneous Notes and Memorabilia.
Scope and Contents
The Edward Claudius Herrick Papers date from 1827 to 1862 and are arranged in five series: I. CORRESPONDENCE, II. SCIENTIFIC FILES, III. YALE UNIVERSITY FILES, IV. FINANCIAL AND LEGAL FILES, and V. MISCELLANEOUS NOTES AND MEMORABILIA.
With few exceptions, CORRESPONDENCE is only incoming letters. Most of the letters deal with scientific subjects; in particular there is a great deal of correspondence about the aurora borealis. Among the important correspondents are Louis Agassiz, James D. Dana, Thaddeus William Harris, Elias Loomis, Lambert-Adolphe Jacques Quetelet, William C. Redfield, Samuel H. Scudder, Benjamin Silliman, Benjamin Silliman, Jr., and William Tully.
SCIENTIFIC FILES is primarily concerned with Herrick's work in astronomy and entomology. His memoranda, notes, and observations of the aurora borealis constitute a major part of the astronomical papers. Herrick's entomological specialty was the Hessian fly, which he spent nine years studying. The papers representing this study include notes, observations, and drawings.
Herrick served as librarian of Yale College from 1843 to 1858. In YALE UNIVERSITY FILES are many records concerning the early years of the Yale College Library. Included are catalogues, invoices, and memoranda regarding books Yale had or wanted to purchase.
After the death of James Kingsley, Herrick assumed responsibility for the Yale College triennial catalogues. His papers include memoranda on the writing and publishing of the catalogue, and information for Yale classes 1847, 1850, 1853, 1856, 1859, and 1862.
FINANCIAL AND LEGAL FILES contains both personal financial records and the business records of Herrick and Noyes, Booksellers.
Of interest in MISCELLANEOUS NOTES AND MEMORANDA are memoranda concerning New Haven, especially the bicentennial celebration and the colonial burial ground.
The papers were transferred from Beinecke Rare Book Library in 1973. Herrick's papers as Yale University treasurer will be found in the Yale archives record group, Finance and Administration, Treasurer's Records (YRG 5-B).
Biographical / Historical
Edward C. Herrick: Yale University librarian, 1843-1858; treasurer of Yale College, 1852-1862; scientist active in investigating the Hessian fly; also interested in astronomy.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Astronomy; Auroras; Booksellers and bookselling; Entomology; Hessian fly; Science; New Haven (Conn.) -- History; Account books; Librarians; Scientists; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873; Barnard, Frederick A. P. (Frederick Augustus Porter), 1809-1889; Dana, James Dwight, 1813-1895; Duyckinck, Evert A. (Evert Augustus), 1816-1878; Harris, Thaddeus William, 1795-1856; Harris, William Thaddeus, 1826-1854; Herrick, Edward Claudius, 1811-1862; Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William), 1792-1871; Jones, George, 1800-1870; Loomis, Elias, 1811-1889; Quetelet, Adolphe, 1796-1874; Redfield, W. C. (William C.), 1789-1857; Scudder, Samuel Hubbard, 1837-1911; Silliman, Benjamin, 1779-1864; Silliman, Benjamin, 1816-1885; Tully, William, 1785-1859; Herrick and Noyes; Yale University -- Curricula; Yale University -- Officals and employees; Yale University. Library; Yale University. Treasurer
- Correspondence, 1831-1862; Series I; 2' (4 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  CORRESPONDENCE is arranged alphabetically by writer. Letters by a particular writer have been arranged chronologically. An asterisk indicates that there are more than ten letters from a particular writer. A complete list of correspondents can be found in the added entries list.
  Folders with asterisks (*) contain ten or more items.
  - Agassiz - Arnold, 1834-1860 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Babcock - Bancroft, 1832-1860 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Barnard, Frederic A.P. (*), 1831-1859 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Barnard, H. - Boyd (*), 1838-1861 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Brace - Burritt, 1838-1862 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Canales - Cleveland, 1837-1860 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Coates - Curtis (*), 1838-1861 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dabney - Daggett, 1840-1854 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dana, James D. (*), 1832-1845 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Davies - Drake, 1833-1859 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Duffield - Dyer (*), 1838-1862 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Edgar - Evarts, 1835-1862 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Farnam - French, 1835-1859 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Geer - Gleason, 1845-1862 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Goodrich - Guthrie, 1831-1861 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Haile -Hare, 1834-1858 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Harris, Thaddeus W. (*), 1834-1855 (Box 2, Folder 18-20)
  - Harris, William T. (*), 1849-1851 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Harrison - Hentz, 1838-1861 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Herrick, E.P., 1848 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Herrick, Henry, 1838-1853 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Herrick, Jedediah, 1837 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Herrick, John P., 1837 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Herrick, Seldon, 1832 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Herschel - Howe, 1838-1861 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Hubbard, Joseph S. (*), 1845-1850 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Hubbard, O. - Huntington, 1848-1861 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Ingersoll - Jones (*), 1837-1862 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Jordon - Judson (*), 1837-1852 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - [Kent?] - Knox, 1835-1862 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Lambert - Lee, 1842-1859 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Leeds, Charles H. (*), 1855-1862 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Lefroy - Linsley, E., 1843-1859 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Linsley, James H. (*), 1839-1842 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Loomis, Elias (*), 1835-1860 (Box 3, Folder 38-48)
  - Lovell - Lyman, 1840-1849 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - McEwen - [Markoe?], 1839-1858 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Marsh, Benjamin V. (*), 1859-1861 (Box 3, Folder 51-52)
  - Martin - Myers, 1833-1860 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Newcomb - Onderdonk, 1833-1861 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Palfrey - Palmer, J. (*), 1852-1867 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Palmer, R. - Perkins, 1836-1860 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Pickering - Platt, 1836-1861 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Polk - Punderson, 1831-1863 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Quaritch - Redfield, J. (*), 1839-1861 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Redfield, William C. (*), 1835-1856 (Box 4, Folder 60-63)
  - Ripley - Runkle, 1837-1858 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Sabine - Scudder, 1837-1862 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Seeger - Shorter, 1837-1861 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Sibley - Skinner, 1834-1863 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Smith, A. - Smith, W. (*), 1837-1862 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Sophocles - Swan, 1833-1861 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Taft - Townsend, 1843-1861 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Trumbull, James H. (*), 1849-1862 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Tuckerman - Tully S., 1851-1856 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Tully, William (*), 1831-1855 (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Tuthill - Tyler, 1837-1859 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Vallot - Wayland, 1833-1860 (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - Webster - Yale College, 1832-1862 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Letters of recommendation written by Edward C. Herrick, 1852, 1857 (Box 4, Folder 77)
- Scientific Files, 1827-1862; Series II; 2' (4 boxes)
  SCIENTIFIC FILES have been arranged alphabetically and primarily contain material concerning astronomy and entomology.
  - Astronomy
    - Aurora borealis observations, 1834-1837 (Box 5, Folder 78)
    - Aurora borealis observations and notes, 1827-1858 (Box 5, Folder 79)
    - Aurora borealis: Register of the Aurora Borealis, New Haven, Connecticut volume 1, 1837-1844 (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - Aurora borealis: Register of the Aurora Borealis, New Haven, Connecticut volume 2, 1845-1850 (Box 5, Folder 81)
    - Aurora borealis: Register of the Aurora Borealis, New Haven, Connecticut volume 3, 1851-1854 (Box 5, Folder 82)
    - Charts and diagrams, 1837-1860 (Box 6, Folder 83)
    - Comets: listing of comets seen by scientists, Circa 1843 (Box 6, Folder 84)
    - Comets: memorandum, notes and diagrams, 1843 (Box 6, Folder 85)
    - Memoranda on shooting stars and meteors
      General
      See: box 15
    - Notes, Circa 1837-1844 (Box 6, Folder 86-87)
    - Notes on the antiquities of shooting stars, Circa 1837 (Box 6, Folder 88)
    - Observations, 1835-1862 (Box 6, Folder 89)
    - Yale College Observatory notebooks, 1842-1843, 1860 (Box 6, Folder 90)
  - Entomology
    - Bibliography, Circa 1836 (Box 6, Folder 91)
    - Drawings and sketches, 1832-1833, undated (Box 6, Folder 92)
    - Memoranda and notes on the Hessian fly, 1832, undated (Box 6, Folder 93)
    - Notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 94)
    - Notes, especially pertaining to the Hessian fly, Circa 1834 (Box 7, Folder 95)
    - Observations, 1829-1841, undated (Box 7, Folder 96)
    - Observations on insects which attack wheat and rye, 1833-1841 (Box 7, Folder 97)
    - Reports by other scientists, 1823-1834 (Box 7, Folder 98)
    - Tables and descriptions, 1834 (Box 7, Folder 99)
  - Meteorological observations, 1826-1831, 1836-1838, 1860 (Box 7, Folder 100-101)
  - Surveying books, 1840-1843 (Box 7, Folder 102)
  - Memoranda and notes on various scientific subjects, undated (Box 7, Folder 103)
  - Newspaper clippings on astronomy and meteorology, 1826-1861 (Box 7, Folder 104)
  - Newspaper clippings on various scientific subjects, 1828-1855 (Box 7, Folder 105)
  - Memoranda on shooting stars and meteors, 1837 (Box 15)
- Yale University Files, 1823-1862; Series III; 7.5" (2 boxes)
  YALE UNIVERSITY FILES are arranged alphabetically and primarily contain material on the Yale College Library and the Triennial Catalogue.
  - Yale College Library
    - Accounts, 1846 (Box 8, Folder 106)
    - Additions to the Yale College Library, 1832-1834 (Box 8, Folder 107)
    - Catalogue and invoice of books imported by Professor Silliman, Circa 1843 (Box 8, Folder 108)
    - Catalogue of books bequeathed by Dr. Jacob Porter, 1847 (Box 8, Folder 109)
    - Catalogue of books bought by Professor A.D. Stanley, 1837 (Box 8, Folder 110)
    - Catalogue of duplicates, 1855 (Box 8, Folder 111)
    - Catalogue of pamphlets, 1828-1831 (Box 8, Folder 112)
    - Donations, 1823-1843 (Box 8, Folder 113)
    - Financial memoranda, 1823-1853 (Box 8, Folder 114)
    - Inventories and listings of books, periodicals journals, and newspapers, 1821-1852 (Box 8, Folder 115)
    - Invoices for books purchased, volume 1, Circa 1843 (Box 8, Folder 116)
    - Invoices for books purchased, volume 2, Circa 1843 (Box 8, Folder 117)
    - Invoices for books purchased, volume 3, Circa 1843 (Box 8, Folder 118)
    - Invoices for books purchased, volume 4, 1844-1845 (Box 8, Folder 119)
    - Invoices for books purchased, volume 1A, 1845 (Box 8, Folder 120)
    - Invoices for books purchased, volume 2A, 1845-1846 (Box 8, Folder 121)
    - Listing of books wanted for the library, undated (Box 8, Folder 122)
    - Memoranda for the library catalogue, 1857 (Box 8, Folder 123)
    - Memoranda of books purchased or given, Circa 1843 (Box 8, Folder 124)
    - Payments for books purchased, 1797-1860, Circa 1860 (Box 8, Folder 125)
    - Yale College Law Library appraisal, 1845 (Box 8, Folder 126)
    - Yale College Law Library catalogue, 1847 (Box 8, Folder 127)
  - Memoranda for diplomas, 1854 (Box 9, Folder 128)
  - Memoranda for degrees, 1855 (Box 9, Folder 129)
  - "Obituary Record of Graduates of Yale College deceased during the academical year 1860-1861" (Box 9, Folder 130)
  - Triennial catalogues
    - Memoranda concerning the writing and printing of the catalogue, undated (Box 9, Folder 131)
    - Yale College Catalogue with annotations of the residences for the class of 1805 (Box 9, Folder 131a)
    - Summary of the information in the catalogue, 1847 (Box 9, Folder 132)
    - Memoranda relating to the catalogue, 1850 (Box 9, Folder 133)
    - Memoranda for the catalogue, 1853 (Box 9, Folder 134)
    - Memoranda for the catalogue with memoranda on degrees conferred, 1856, 1859, 1862 (Box 9, Folder 135-137)
  - Biographical notes on Yale graduates, undated (Box 9, Folder 138)
  - Lists about Yale College students and professors, undated (Box 9, Folder 139)
  - Notes on education, undated (Box 9, Folder 140)
- Financial and Legal Files, 1828-1854; Series IV; 3' (4 boxes)
  FINANCIAL AND LEGAL FILES are arranged alphabetically and contain a large amount of material relating to Herrick & Noyes.
  - Account and deeds relating to the estate of Sarah Pierpont, 1836-1840 (Box 10, Folder 141)
  - Accounts for the estates of [Ruamah?] and William Canada, 1853-1854 (Box 10, Folder 142)
  - Bank account and listing of bills payable, 1837, 1852-1854 (Box 10, Folder 143)
  - Business (Personal) memoranda, 1835-1838 (Box 10, Folder 144)
  - Cashbook, 1836-1853 (Box 10, Folder 145)
  - Private cash book A, 1828-1841 (Box 10, Folder 146)
  - Private cash book B, 1841-1843 (Box 10, Folder 147)
  - Documents concerned with the application of Hannah Mansfield for a pension, 1839 (Box 10, Folder 148)
  - Expenditures and receipts for Hannah Herrick, 1836-1846 (Box 10, Folder 149)
  - Herrick and Noyes
    - Bills and notes payable, 1835-1854 (Box 11, Folder 150)
    - Cashbook, 1835-1847 (Box 11, Folder 151)
    - Circulars and accounts, 1835-1843 (Box 11, Folder 152)
    - Commission book, 1835-1846 (Box 11, Folder 153)
    - Inventory, 1838 (Box 11, Folder 154)
    - Letterbook also containing personal notes and memoranda of E.C. Herrick, 1845-1855 (Box 11, Folder 155)
    - Day books, 1835-1844 (Box 12, Folder 155a)
    - Ledger, 1835-1838 (Box 13, Folder 155b)
- Miscellaneous Notes and Memorabilia, 1836-1860; Series V; 0.25; (1 box)
  MISCELLANEOUS NOTES AND MEMORABILIA is arranged alphabetically. Most important are the notes and memoranda on New Haven.
  - Miscellaneous Notes
    - Bells: notes on bells and their tones, 1841, 1854, undated (Box 14, Folder 156)
    - Biographical and genealogical notes on individuals and families, undated (Box 14, Folder 157)
    - Etymology: memoranda, 1855, undated (Box 14, Folder 158)
    - New Haven
      - Bicentennial: correspondence, minutes from committee meetings and reports, 1838 (Box 14, Folder 159)
      - Burial Ground: copies of the epitaphs on gravestones, Circa 1851 (Box 14, Folder 160)
      - Memoranda and notes on New Haven and Yale University, Circa 1836-1860 (Box 14, Folder 161)
      - Periodicals published in New Haven, undated (Box 14, Folder 162)
    - Quotations and sayings collected by Herrick, 1853, 1861, undated (Box 14, Folder 163)
    - Religion: miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 14, Folder 164)
    - Review of a book by James D. Dana, undated (Box 14, Folder 165)
    - Title pages from various books, undated (Box 14, Folder 166)
    - Unidentified notes, undated (Box 14, Folder 167)
  - Memorabilia
    - Diary and memoranda books, 1833-1854 (Box 14, Folder 168)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1828-1851 (Box 14, Folder 169)
    - Photograph of a framed bust of E.C. Herrick, undated (Box 14, Folder 170)